{
  "reference_number": "158",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Set a net zero emission target by 2050 and the Climate Change Commission advises on how to get there by that date. It has to be\n bold, be written in legislation and there has to be immediate investment in figuring out how we realistic achieve that. We've waited\n\n long enough to have a government that takes this seriously...we haven't got time to debate what figure we should go for at this point\n in history."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Be bold and invest in technology advances and good old back to basic land replanting. We can do it here. Strong targets mean\n\n quicker change."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Don't cheat. We have a poor sustainability footprint per capita in New Zealand and focusing what we can do domestically will not only\n reap \"my back yard\" environmental benefits but if we do it well enough can also be economically beneficial through OFFERING\n international carbon units with our own strong, world leading, something to talk about on an international platform, environmental\n\n safeguards. Aotearoa is rather special and we should be looking after this natural environment that draws such attention\n internationally (people don't come here for the theme parks...)"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "For example if a government who prefer to conclude that climate change isn't real or unclean air isn't the problem? Make a really good\n\n bill that puts targets in place, link it with renewable, clean energy and invest in that and projects which help people live sustainably\n and solve the problems of modern living, either by offering alternative, greener solutions or by reducing, reusing and recycling."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Incremental targets are the way forward. SMART goals. Get tougher with each 5 years. Invest more money alongside the emission\n\n reduction budget and ensure that there is a good mechanism for people and companies with smart ideas to access relevant funding\n and support (I've got a tonne of great ideas and no-one from ATEED has ever called me back when making contact with them for\n\n example)."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Make is SMART to start with. Don't give governments the power to change it. Many of us voted Labour as ex Green supporters\nunderstanding that if voted in we might have a government who is willing to take a firm stance on climate change action."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Should also be asked to take into account opportunity cost of continuing to do business as usual in New Zealand. And I would love to\nsee advice given regarding impact of switching investments and subsidies from fossil fuels to green technologies on all of the\n\nproposed considerations in the medium term. For example, if you stop giving subsidies to oil exploration in the hundreds of millions\nand invest in green-tech/ solar subsidy (as they did in Oz) how does that affect fuel poverty?"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Personally, I'm frustrated with the amount of time it takes to get action. Not a lot of point in having a budget of 5 years if you don't\n\nknow what you're going to do for 2 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Fine balancing act of creating strong motivation for change and not penalising the poorer members of society or annoying\nbusinesses. Could you just figure out the emission cost of every New Zealander per year and give businesses a tax credit for\n\nreleasing staff to plant their emission value in native trees per year?? Great team building opportunity and an extension of the tree-\nplanting. Encourage planting of marginal land by offering further subsidies and grants for high value cash/carbon sequestering crops\n\nsuch as hemp/manuka."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But I also think it should have the capacity to decision make...much the same as our coalition government, to keep us on track you\nneed impartiality and focus on the required outcome. Be the first in the world. Otherwise, like in many other instance the general\n\npopulation feel that money is spent on commissions only for government to totally ignore them for the sake of other concerns."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We're going to need to adapt and tying in solutions to both zero carbon and adaptation to climate change seems appropriate."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
